[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
developers are you ready it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
when you can make faster decisions
there's no telling what you'll create
ready set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
this is jeremy jung for software
engineering radio today i'm talking with
paul smith
paul is the creator of the lucky web
framework and he currently works at
github
today we're going to talk about the
crystal programming language and the
lucky web framework
paul welcome to software engineering
radio thank you so much happy to be here
there are a lot of languages for
software developers to choose from
what excited you about crystal yeah
that's really interesting because
when i first saw crystal i actually was
not interested
at all it basically looked like ruby to
me
and so i just think okay so it's a
faster ruby
and typically if i want to learn a new
language i want something that feels
really different that
pushes the boundaries on things i
started getting more interested
in compile time guarantees i worked at
thoughtbot
previous to github and previously to
roku
and people were starting to get really
into typed languages um
some people were starting to get into
haskell which is like you know the
the big one that i guess is probably one
of the more
type safe but also hard to use languages
right
but also elm which has a good focus on
developer
happiness and productivity and
explaining what's going on
and as they were talking about how they
were writing fewer tests and it was
easier to
refactor it started becoming clear to me
that that's something i want
one of the things somebody said was if
the computer
can check the code for you let the
computer do that
rather than you or rather than a test so
i started to get really interested in
that
i was also interested in elixir which is
another fantastic language i did a lot
of work with elixir
i built a library called bamboo which is
an email
library and another called x machina
which is
what a lot of people use for creating
test data
so i was really into it for a while and
at first i'm like wow
i love functional and then i realize
like i can do a lot
like a lot of the stuff i like about
this i can do with objects
i just need to rethink things so that it
uses objects
rather than whatever random dsl because
i mean
when you think about functions right
like you've got this big bucket of
functions and you gotta pass in
all the parameters right whereas you
know in a lot of cases i feel like if
you have those instance variables
available in the object then the actual
functions can be a lot
simpler in some ways yeah totally
that's like a huge focus and making the
object small
so that it doesn't have too much but
that's how i began to feel with elixir
is that i'm like
i just have 50 arts and most of them i
don't care about
like i want to look at what's important
to this method
to this method it's you know this
argument but with functions you're like
which thing's important
does the first thing probably not that's
probably just the thing i'm passing
everywhere
and so i like that ability to kind of
focus in and know like this
object has these two instance variables
everywhere
yeah it's kind of interesting to get
your perspective
because it seemed like you were pretty
deep into elixir if you had created
bamboo and ex machina and stuff like
that so
it's kind of interesting yeah i was like
yeah
and and then i started missing objects
and luckily with crystal and ruby you
still get a lot of the functional stuff
like you can pass blocks around
um that's functions you can use
functions but
it's not the other way in elixir you
can't use objects it doesn't exist
and then the type safety yeah i'm just
like i still run into so many errors you
know so frustrating
yeah i don't want to do that
the main benefit i got out of elixir
compared to rails
um which is what i had been using and
still use a lot of
was speed that was really big in terms
of
bugs caught about the same mostly
because it's still
for the most part dynamically typed
language with very few
compile-time guarantees so i'd still get
the nil errors i'd still
mess up calls to different functions and
things like that
and so that's where i ran into crystal
it has
the nice syntax i like from elixir and
ruby
it's also very very fast faster
than go in some benchmarks so it's quick
plenty fast for what i need
and it has those compile time guarantees
like
checking for nils that's a huge one
and it also makes the type system very
friendly so it does a lot of
type inference and very powerful macros
so you can
reduce some of the boilerplate and so
that's when i kind of started getting
into crystal was
seeing elixir i still got a lot of these
bugs that i was running into with rails
but i like the speed but i don't want to
use haskell
and elm doesn't exist on the back end so
i started looking at crystal
and so it sort of sounds like there's
this spectrum right you have
ruby and you have elixir where you don't
necessarily specify your types so the
compiler can't help you as much and then
you've got haskell
which is very strict right you have a
compiler that
helps you a lot and then there's kind of
languages in between like
for example java and c-sharp and things
like that they've been around for
quite some time how does crystal sort of
compare to
languages like those yeah that's a great
question because i did look at
some of those other ones typescript for
example is huge
kotlin was another one that i had looked
at
because it's java but better basically
that's
the way it's pitched and so far everyone
that's used it has basically said that
and also looking at rust what it came
down to
was how powerful was the type system
so crystal has union types which can be
extremely helpful
and it catches nil java does not have a
good way to do that
kotlin does but also boilerplate
and the macro system crystals is
extremely powerful
elixir also has a very powerful macro
system
but crystals is type safe which is even
more fantastic
so basically what that let me do with
lucky was build even more powerful type
safe programs and we can kind of get
into that once we
we talk about lucky and how that was
designed but basically with these other
languages
a lot of what we do in lucky just simply
wouldn't be possible or wouldn't be
possible without
a significant amount of work and
duplication
you covered a few things there one of
the things was macros
what what are macros yeah this is like a
confusing thing it took me a while to
to get what it is but
in ruby for example they have ways
of of meta programming that are not done
at
compile time for most compile-time
languages
compiled languages i should say you need
macros to deduplicate thing and
basically what
a macro does is it generates
code for you the way i think about it
is basically you've got a method or or
it's a macro but it looks like a method
it has code inside of it and it's like
you're copy
pasting whatever is inside of that macro
into wherever you called it from so in
other words
rails has a has many like has many users
has many tasks
that's generating a ton of code for you
so that's how ruby does it
um in crystal has many would be a macro
and it would literally generate a ton of
code and
copy paste that into wherever you called
it um so it's just a way to
reduce boilerplate so in the case of
dynamic languages like
ruby when you talk about meta
programming that's having
i guess a function that is generating
code at
runtime right and yes
the macro is sort of doing something
similar
except it's generating that code at
compile time is that kind of the
distinction
that's the way i look at it there are
people much smarter than me that
probably have a more
specific answer about what the
differences are
but in my mind in practical usage that's
what it comes down to in my mind
let's say there's a problem in that code
what do you get shown in the debugger
debugging macros
is definitely harder than debugging your
regular code
for that exact reason it is generating a
code so what crystal does
there's different ways of doing this but
i like crystal's approach
and it'll show you the final result of
the code
and it'll point to the line in the
generated code that caused the issue
and tell you which macro generated it
now it's still not ideal because that
code isn't code
you wrote it's called the macro
generated
but it does allow you to see what the
macro generated
and why it might be an issue part of
that can be solved
by writing error messages and error
handling as part of the macro
so in other words making sure if you're
expecting a string literal
you can have a check at the top that
checks for it to be a string literal
i wouldn't use them by default but it's
great for i think a framework
where you have a lot of boilerplatey
things that you're literally typing
in every single model or every single
controller
and that people kind of get used to
that's well tested that has
nice error messages in my own personal
code though
i pretty much never use macros they're
only in the libraries that i write
another thing you mentioned is how
crystal helps you detect
nils or or nulls yeah um how does how
does the language do that
it actually uses union types for that
some
languages that have this they'll have an
optional type
which is basically a wrapper around
whatever real type
like an optional string or optional int
and you have to unwrap it the way
crystal does it
is you would say string or nil
and there's a little bit of syntactic
sugar so you can just say string with a
question mark at the end
but that gets expanded to string or a
nil type
so then within that method the compiler
knows that this could be a string
could be a nil and there's a little bit
of sugar there where the compiler
if you say if whatever variable you have
it's gonna know that within that if it
is not
nil and in the else it is so there's a
little bit of sugar there as well
but that's basically how they handle it
and there are ways to
force the compiler uh just say hey this
thing is not now you can call not nil on
it
that's a little i would avoid that
because maybe the compiler is right and
it really is now
or maybe you change the method later and
then it can become new
and you're going to get a runtime error
there but it does have those escape
patches because sometimes you just need
the quick and dirty
and you can if you need to as long as
you don't tell the compiler that
then you will actually have a compiler
error if you have a method that takes in
let's say some type of object or a nil
and then you don't account for the fact
that like it could be nil
then the compiler actually won't let you
compile is that correct
that is correct so for example
if you just had a method that's like
print email
and it accepts a user or new i'm not
saying i would
do that but let's say that it does and
you just tried within that method to do
user
dot email to print the user's email
it's gonna fail and tell you that
nil does not have the method email
and so you need to handle that yeah
you're forced to either do an if
or for example you can use try
which is basically a method that says
call call a method on this object
unless it's new if it's nil just return
nil but yes
it kind of forces you to to do that
and and crystal how do you handle
errors because a lot of different
languages they'll have things like
exceptions or they may have result types
what's sort of the the main way in
crystal i'd say
i'd group it into two types of errors
where you have runtime exemptions still
because things do
break not everything is in a perfect
world
inside your type system databases go
down you know redis falls over or
whatever
so you still have runtime exceptions and
then you have the compile time errors
which we kind of just talked about
but in terms of how those runtime
exceptions are handled
it's i don't want to say exactly the
same as ruby because there probably are
some subtle differences but extremely
similar to ruby
and that you're not passing around
errors it's so it's not like go
where you are explicitly handling errors
at every step
you raise it and you can rescue that
error kind of like a try catch in other
languages
and you can also just let it bubble up
and rescue at a higher level
which i personally prefer because not
every error is something that i care
about
and kind of forcing me to handle every
single error
everywhere means that it is harder as a
reader of the code
to tell which errors i should care about
because they're all treated as equal
so i like that in crystal i can say this
particular error in this particular
method i want to handle
in a special way and somewhere up above
the stack
i can just say anything else just print
to 500
log it send it to sentry yeah so it's
very similar to like you said ruby or
any other language that primarily relies
on exceptions like i think
java for example probably falls into the
same category
probably i haven't used it in quite some
time but i imagine it would be similar
you had mentioned that that crystal was
like pretty fast compared to
other languages what are the big
benefits you've gotten from that raw
speed the biggest benefit
i would say is not having to worry so
much
about rendering times in rails
for example you can spend a ton of time
in the view
even though everyone says databases are
slow they're not that slow
in something like rails active record
takes a
huge amount of time to instantiate every
single record
so how does this play on real life you
could for example in lucky if you wanted
to
load a thousand records and print them
on the page and
probably do that in a couple hundred
milliseconds maybe
which is a totally reasonable uh
response time
the same thing in rails would be many
seconds
which is not reasonable in my opinion
and this can be really helpful partly
because um it just means your apps are
faster
people are getting the responses quickly
but also because you have a lot more
flexibility i've built
internal tools where they want to have
the ability
to search all of the inventory or
products or whatever else and they want
to have like a select all
or you know be able to select everything
and in rails you can't just render all
1000 products
because it basically falls over and you
can try and catch stuff but then that
gets complicated
um so you kind of have to paginate but
when you paginate
that makes it hard to select things
across multiple pages
so then you need some kind of javascript
to remember which ones you selected
across pages
and it just balloons the complexity
right if you know
hey we only have eight or 900 products
we're not going to suddenly have 20
000 and lucky you just render them all
put them all on the same page give them
all check boxes and it's
in the user's hands and 200 milliseconds
and you're done you just removed most of
that complexity
so those are some of the ways that that
speed is playing out
and i think one key difference there is
some people think
speed is just about scalability how many
people can be using this
the speed improvements i care about are
the ones where even if you have one
request per day
i want that request to be insanely fast
and so that's kind of what you're
getting with lucky and crystal
when you talk about web applications you
know with
lucky being a web framework a lot of
people point out that
a lot of the work being done is i o
right it's talking to the database
it's making network calls but i guess
you're saying that
rendering that template those are things
that actually having a fast language
it really does make a big difference it
does yeah i
i think the whole database i o thing a
lot of times that's what people
say when they're working with a slow
language if you have a fast one
it's not as big of a deal because this
was the same with phoenix
and elixir like i loved how quickly it
could render
html that was huge and like you said
that opens up
options in terms of not having to rely
on caching
or pagination or things like that yeah
this is huge
i mean an example from work we just
announced github discussions
um and i'm on that team and one of the
big things we were trying to
get working was was performance of the
discussions
show page you could have hundreds of
comments
on that page and we were finding
that most of the time taken was actually
spent rendering the views
and calling methods on the different
objects to render things differently
in the seconds and we can't cache those
reliably
because there are so many different ways
to show that data
if you're a moderator you get certain
buttons if you're
an unverified user like someone who just
signed up
you see a different thing if you're not
signed in you see a different thing
and so you can't reliably cache those
and we had a lot of cool techniques to
kind of get that down
but this is something that if this were
written and lucky
it just would not have been an issue
and and github in particular is written
in
ruby is that correct it is yeah it's
using ruby on rails
and i'm not trying to knock rails i i
really love rails i mean i've been using
it for 12 years
um i like ruby uh but hey if there's
something that could be even better
i'm open to that for sure
you have used rails for 12 years
how would you say that your productivity
compares
in ruby versus in crystal i think that's
tricky it's kind of better and worse
and what i mean by that is i think
crystal i am i'm more productive in
crystal
you do have compile times and we can
talk about that they're not the fastest
they're not the slowest
but i do find that i can write more code
and then compile once and it kind of
just tells me where the problems are
and i have a lot more confidence and i
spend a lot a lot less time banging my
head on like why isn't this thing
working and it's
because i passed the wrong type
somewhere however
ruby has a massive ecosystem so
there are things that exist in ruby that
i would have to rewrite and crystal
and so that for sure no matter how
productive i am in crystal
is not as productive as requiring the
gem and then just using it
so the hope with lucky though is that
we're building up
enough things that you don't have to be
rewriting everything
and the community's also really stepped
up in writing a number of
libraries that are super helpful for web
development
for example somebody just wrote
webdrivers.cr
which makes it so that it can
automatically install
the version of chrome driver that
matches the version of chrome
that you have installed so you don't
have to manage that at all that's
something that was in ruby for a while
and will be in lucky probably in the
next release
so yeah i think it's better it's one of
those things that will get better with
time
so in terms of the actual language
productivity
crystal it sounds like basically a net
positive
but it's more in the the community
aspect and and
how many libraries are available that's
where a lot more time gets taken
i think so and then just the initial
ramping up uh it is a new language and
so there aren't as many stack overflow
questions and answers right there aren't
as many tutorials
so there's definitely some things there
that but like i said those are things
we're working on
especially for 1-0 of lucky try and make
sure we have really good guides
really good error messages we tried to
borrow
a little bit from elm not specific error
messages but just the idea
that an error message should raise
something
human readable and understandable and if
possible
help guide them in the right direction
of what they probably want to do
or at least point them to documentation
to make it easier
so we're trying to help with that as
much as
as we can i kind of want to move into
next more into
your experience building lucky you know
you were a rails developer for many
years
and are there any like specific major
pain points i guess in rails or in your
previous
web development experience that you
wanted to address with lucky
yeah there were um some more specific
than others
some easier to solve in the sense that
the solution is like it works or doesn't
and others that are a little bit more
abstract so i'll talk about some of the
specific things
i often said that i'm into type safety i
don't think that is
quite true and i think it especially if
you haven't used lucky it just doesn't
click what that means or why it matters
because you just think like oh so
you know it'll tell me if i pass an
integer instead of a string like who
cares i'm not
seeing those kinds of errors what i'm
most interested in is compile time
guarantees
whether that's with a type or some other
mechanism
and that's there not just to prevent
bugs but to help you as a developer to
spot problems right away
and give you a nice error so you know
what to do about it
so for example one of the things that
i've seen in basically every framework
i've ever used regardless of
whether it is type safe or not is that
you need to use an http method a verb
and a path so for example if you want to
delete a user you would have forward
slash users forward slash
one to be the id the tricky part is
you have to have the http method delete
for to do the delete
action but sometimes you forget that you
use a regular link and you wonder why
the heck
it just keeps showing you this thing
instead of deleting it
or the particularly insidious one is
when you have a update and a create
one uses post one uses put
if you have an update form and you
forget to put the method put
you get all kinds of routing errors
because it says hey this doesn't exist
and you want well why why doesn't this
exist i can see it right here i've got
the route i've got everything
oh it's because i forgot to put the http
method
is a put and it just wastes time
so that's one of those things where we
wanted to compile time guarantee
and lucky and so i don't want to go too
in depth here
but basically what we did was we made
every controller into a single
class that handled the routing and also
the response
if i understand correctly when
you have a page and you want to link to
a specific user on that page
then you would use this this function
link to and you would pass in the class
that corresponds to showing a user and
then you would pass
parameters into that function like for
example
the id of the user and if you
didn't do that then you would have an
error at compile time
not correct you wouldn't need to like
start the website and then go to the
page and and have it
basically explode which i guess is
typically what you would expect from
most web fabrics or what's worse
it wouldn't explode it would just
generate the wrong link
right and you would have to remember to
click that link or
write an automated test that clicks that
link
so it's really easy for bugs to sneak in
and this just completely
prevents that class of bug as well as
just makes life easier because if you
forget
a parameter while you're developing from
the start
instead of just generating something
with like a nil id
it's going to say hey you forgot this it
just saves a lot of debugging time
and i think it's also more intuitive if
you've ever used rails helpers
or phoenix how any of these man the
conventions
like it's a singular is it plural is it
does it have the name space does it not
have the name space
and lucky that it's gone you just call
the action
the one that you created you call that
exactly as is
it sounds like this is maybe a little
more explicit i guess
yeah it's a little more explicit but i
hesitate
i've heard a couple things in the
programming community
one the rail started is convention over
configuration
which that was huge because you had to
learn the convention but at least once
you did you knew how
the other rails projects work and then
another one i hear is explicit over
implicit i don't buy into either of
those
in particular because sometimes
implicit's better
sometimes explicits better i mean for
example
as a quick example i don't hear anyone
arguing
to bring back the old objective
c where you had to manually reference
and de-reference
memory that is technically more explicit
right but does anyone want to do that no
so
i don't think explicit over implicit you
have to think about it everything needs
to be judged
in its own context and what i think is
even better than convention over
configuration is intuitive over
conventions
meaning you don't even think about it
you don't even need
there doesn't need to be a convention
because you're literally just
calling the thing that you created like
anything else
there's nothing special about that it's
a class just like any other class
and you call a method on it just like
any other method
i think it's tricky because i think it's
also easy to say explicit over implicit
and make your code super hard to follow
and it's like yes it's more explicit but
also i just wrote 20 lines of code
instead of one and those 20 lines could
differ
because i do it differently than the
other guy or girl
calling all developers there's no
telling what you can create when you
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris
are you ready to build the applications
you want however you want them
are you ready to develop applications
faster than ever collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today
enter systems iris data platform ready
set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
another thing about lucky that's
a little different is that for
templating instead of having
somebody write html and embedding
language code in it
you instead have people write crystal
code so could you kind of explain sort
of
why you made that decision and what the
benefits are
yeah sure so a lot of things actually
with lucky
kind of i did not want to do or
were definitely not how i started doing
things and it just kind of
moved in that direction based on the
goals
and and i think that's part of what
makes lucky different
is that we don't say here's how i want
to do it we say here's what i want to do
and i want it to be easy simple and bug
free
so what we started with was using
templating languages just like you'd use
in almost any
anything where you write your html
and then you interpolate values in it at
the time
i wrote lucky and this may be changed
now
you could not use a method that accepted
a function or a block as what it would
be called in crystal
and have that output correctly in the
template i think it just blew up i don't
remember this was
two years ago three years ago the other
problem
i was having was it's not just a
template
any bigger size framework also has
partials or you know fragments or
includes or whatever you want to call it
it also has layouts where you can inject
different html and different parts of
your html layout
and those are all things that a person
has to learn when they're learning your
framework
what are these methods called for
generating a partial or for calling a
partial
or injecting stuff in in different
layers of the way out
and it's also more stuff that i have to
write and
with lucky like there was already a lot
to write we were building the orm
and the automated test drivers and the
router
and like everything so i can't afford to
just
do stuff like everyone else does it if
it's not
pulling its weight so eventually i
started experimenting with
building html using classes
and regular crystal methods
some of the requirements for me when i
was building it was
it had to match the structure of html
and
it had to be very easy to refactor
meaning i can pull something out
into a new method and it just works so
easy refactoring
and then i also need to be able to do
layouts with it
the reason for that is elm also uses
code to generate html
however it is not approachable to
a newcomer if for example you have a
designer and they pull open an
elm file and try and look at what that
what that generates
no way i mean i'm a programmer i still
don't know what it generates without
really looking through elm and that's
partly because
you are generating data objects so
arrays of arrays
or maps or whatever else so i didn't
want that it has to be approachable to
people and
look and be structured like html
and so we actually were able to do that
i don't know if i need to go into huge
detail but basically you can
say hey i want a div inside of that i
want an h1
underneath that i want another div and
you're not building arrays and maps and
anything else
what that provides is actually a lot of
things that i did not think of
one super easy refactoring if you have
a link in a particular page
and you don't want to copy that over and
over and over extract a method
and you call it like any other method
there's nothing to learn
it's just a method like anything else it
can accept arguments just like anything
else
your conditionals work you can extract
that into a component which is basically
another class
and it tells you explicitly here's what
i need to run
and it renders the thing you always have
the correct closing tag
i have been bitten so many times by
shifting stuff around
and forgetting a closing tag and my
whole page looks wonky
and i have to go through layers of
indentation
that just doesn't happen if you forget
and end
so you would have a do end when you're
creating these blocks
it blows up it's like hey you're missing
one and the coolest part is you just add
an end in there
and you run the crystal formatter and it
re-indents everything perfectly
and then on top of that that wasn't
enough like i just loved how easy it was
to refactor and use
you don't have to split up your code
from your template like in rails you
would have a helper
so you've got like here's your template
but then you might have a helper and a
totally separate file
if you've got something that pertains to
just that
page you can just extract a method it's
right there
but this also made it so we can do
layouts
without any special work your layout is
basically a class
you would say here's my class with the
head
it renders the head it renders html body
or whatever
and then it calls a content method or a
sidebar method or whatever else
and your page so if you want to render a
list of users
inherits from that class and implements
a content method
or a sidebar method and so when that's
rendered out it just calls those methods
so we got all of that for free if you
look at our view rendering code
it's 50 lines because basically we use a
macro
and give it a list of tags like you know
paragraph h1 h2 whatever
and generate a bunch of methods and and
that's basically it
so from an implementation perspective
it's extremely simple
plus you get all these niceties around
refactoring
is super easy it's super easy to tell
what a page needs to render at the top
of the page you just say
you know i need a user i need a
paginator i need a current user
so you know what that page needs you
don't get that with a template
and you get all the power of crystal for
rendering layouts however you want
that all basically came for free so it
was kind of a happenstance that
templates weren't working and this just
worked out better people
a lot of people when they see this are
like what the heck is this i hate it
and i always just say just give it a try
just give it a try for a little bit so
far
one person has said like okay i don't
like it and you can use templates if you
want we've actually built that in
but everybody else is like now that i've
used it i love it
what it sounds like is in a lot of
javascript frameworks for example like
react
there's this concept of components right
and
so you can create what looks like
new html tags but really has other html
in it like let's say you have a a list
of
businesses and maybe you have a
component that would have
all the business details in it
it sounds like in the case of lucky you
kind of
can do the same thing it's just that
your component would be
in the form of a crystal class and so
there isn't any new
syntax and you're not mixing different
languages like you're not mixing html
and javascript instead everything is
just using
crystal exactly you have two options you
can extract a private method
because sometimes it's just a small
thing you want to extract
only used by one page just do a method
if not extract a class and the cool part
about all of this
is that you don't need to restructure
anything
meaning you can start with everything in
one method in your content
method now you pull out just a little
bit into a private method
and then if that's not enough cool pull
that out into a class
so you're not forced into just pulling
out classes all over the place if you
don't need one
it really worked out kind of really well
because it also makes testing easier you
can
pull out a class component that just
does one thing
and you can instantiate just that
component and test
just that html and once again this is
very easy because it's a class
you call it and run it like any other
class and so that's been a big goal of
lucky is try to reduce and this also
comes down to the whole like convention
over configuration
is how do we just make it so there is no
convention
it's just intuitive like if you know how
to extract and refactor
a crystal class you know how to extract
and refactor stuff for
a page in lunky automatically
and i mean of course there's still some
degree of learning and experimentation
but it's the same paradigms if you want
to include
methods in multiple pages use a module
just like any other module
so that was very much a goal and that's
part of
other parts of lucky for example
querying
in something like rails the model is for
creating updating reading everything
in lucky you do create a model and we
use macros to actually generate other
classes for you
but you have a query object that is a
class
what am i passing into my query object
what does that look like
let's say you have a user by default
it generates a user colon colon
base query so basically you have this
new object
name spaced under the model and by
default the generators generate
another file and basically what that
does is it creates a new class
called user query that inherits from
that user base query class
what you would do in your controller or
action or anywhere
say user query dot new by default that
just gives you a new query
that would query everything in the
database
unless of course you overrode initialize
and did something else
then it would use that scope so if you
wanted to further filter down
you would call for example if you wanted
the name to be paul
it would be userquery.new dot name
parens paul as a string because
lucky generates methods for every column
on the model
with compile-time guarantees so if you
typo that method
it's going to blow up if you rename the
column later it's going to blow up
if you accidentally give it nil it's
going to blow up
and tell you to use something else but
that's how you would do it you say dot
name
is paul or we also have type specific
criteria methods
you can do things like dot age dot gt
for greater than 30. and so you have
this very flexible query language that's
all completely type safe
so in your scopes if you wanted to do
something like
recently published for a post inside
that method
you would do something like published at
dot gt
for greater than one dot week dot the go
and you can chain that so you could do
post query.new.recentlypublished
dot authored by paul or whatever
so that's basically how it works you
just have these methods that
are chained that you can build upon
in pretty much any way you want in a lot
of
applications now people use javascript
frameworks whether it's
react or vue or angular what does
integrating with
javascript libraries and frameworks look
like in lucky i think easier than a lot
in the sense that you can generate a
lucky project
with different modes so when you
initialize a project you can use just
the command line
with some flags or the default is to
walk you through a wizard
which will say do you want api only in
which case you know it won't even have
html pages
or the default which is a full app
what that does is it generates webpack
config for you
it sets up your public assets and images
so that they can be copied and
fingerprinted
and so out of the box it already has a
basic
webpack setup for you that handles css
it handles most of your es6 javascript
type stuff that people typically like
that's just handled out of the box if
you want to include
react or vue you would include that just
like any other webpack
project in terms of building it and it's
actually a little simpler we use
laravel mix on top of webpack
which is basically a thin javascript
layer
that calls webpack underneath the hood
if you want a full single page app
that's also totally supported you would
basically have just one html page
that you know has the basic html
and body tags and within that mounts
your app
so whatever that is for your language
and view it might be
just a tag that's like main app and then
in your js
you would initialize that tag
with your app and we have fallback
routing so that you can do client-side
routing
if you want it's not particularly well
documented
which is the biggest problem some people
are helping with that because a number
of people have done react in view
and so hopefully those will be fleshed
out a little bit more but it's totally
supported
in the long term though we've got plans
to
make it so you don't even need those
types of frameworks quite as much
since we already have class components
and a bunch of other things
i'm working on a way to add typesafe
interactivity to html
so you're not writing the javascript
you're writing crystal for the most part
and it can interface with javascript and
you can run you know use react and view
inside of it
but a lot of your simple open close
if anything like that is going to be
handled
client-side but written with crystal and
server interactions will also those will
be sent
over an ajax request but will also be
type safe when you call the actions and
do all the html rendering
similar to live wire for laravel
or live view by phoenix but with some
some differences that's not done yet but
it will be and i think it's going to be
really exciting i've got a proof of
concept up locally and
it's really awesome we had a previous
episode on on live view and i think the
possibilities of of things like that are
really
interesting of being able to
not have to have this sort of separation
between
your javascript front end and your
server back and yet still be able to
have the kind of interactivity people
expect
yeah i think it could be cool and that's
also where speed comes into play
when you're doing interactions like that
you you don't want to wait even 100
even 50 milliseconds is noticeable
for those types of interactions and so
phoenix also fast
really fast template language uh
basically gets compiled down to elixir
and so that helps a lot i do think
there's some big flaws that i've seen
in some other implementation well i
don't want to say flaws that sounds a
little overly harsh but things that i
personally are just deal breakers for me
and one of those
is some client-side interactions
have to be instantaneous they just have
to be
if i click on my avatar in the top right
i expect the menu that has settings and
logout to be
instant if there is any kind of latency
in the network and it takes 200
milliseconds even
that's going to be a weird interaction
and it's going to feel like your app is
broken
and of course that's exacerbated by
people not in your country this is
another problem people are doing these
things
deploying servers in their own country
put a vpn
in front of your computer in australia
or
even the uk 400 milliseconds
that's just you can't do that for a
settings menu or for opening a modal
and so there needs to be some way to do
those interactions
instantaneously livewire by laravel
the same guy that wrote it built alpine
js
which is kind of it looks a little bit
like vue
but it doesn't have a virtual dom it
operates with the dom that you generate
that's what it uses for client side
interactivity
so you can do the server side stuff
which
i mean if latency is there if you're
submitting a comment look there's no way
around it
you've got to hit the server right but
if you're opening and showing something
a menu a tab a modal
that's instantaneous and is handled by
alpine so
lucky's actually going to use that along
with
our own server rendered stuff to do
client-side
interactions instantaneously so
alpine it's a javascript front-end
framework
you said similar to view without the
virtual dom and
it sounds like what you're planning is
to be able to write
crystal code and have that generate
alpine code is that right that's correct
because it's mostly
inline and it can't do everything but
most of what i want from client-side
interactions are typically
super simple things i want to open and
close something
i want to show tabs and those are things
that alpine's
incredibly good at because you don't
need a separate javascript file
we can just generate something that says
it uses x
as its kind of modifier x dash click
toggle the thing true or false toggle
open to true or false and
x if or x show and then
if it's open or not those are things
that we can very easily generate on the
back end
and make type safe because we can say
you know this has to be a boolean
and here's the action and all those
things are then type safe but you can
still do javascript if you want
so you can still use javascript
functions in there with your alpine if
you need to
yeah that sounds like the distinction
between that
and like a live view or a live wire
is that my understanding is with those
solutions
you're shipping over basically diffs
in your html and that's how it's
determining
what to change whereas you're saying
like
you may still have some of that but
there's certain interactions
where you just want to run javascript
locally on
the person's client and you should still
be able to do that even if you are doing
this sort of
sending diffs over the wire for other
things yeah exactly um alpine's made for
that
the biggest the biggest key
differentiator between
livewire live view is the type safety
all those nice things that you get in
lucky
you're going to get also for your
client-side interactions
so if you have an action and you have a
typo or something
it's going to blow up it's going to tell
you if you forget something if you miss
the wrong type i mean
and this is something that's very hard
in the front end world
because you either have to run an
automated test to make sure you catch
these
or the worst you have to open up the
console
because like why isn't this working i
don't know now i have to dig into the
console it's not even where you
typically want to see logs
and so being able to shift that to
where you're used to seeing errors and
before you even have to
open the browser i think that's going to
be a huge deal i think on the the server
side
testing is pretty well understood in
terms of
you know especially if you have api
endpoints
or you have just regular server code
like people know how to test that
but on the client side there's like so
many different ways of doing it it feels
like
and a lot of them involve spinning up
browsers
and get kind of complicated and so
yeah it'll be interesting to see if you
can shift more of that to
the the server environment that a lot of
people are used to yeah
i think it'll be cool we'll see how it
goes and yeah i do think
there's definitely complexity that comes
with moving it to javascript especially
if you have a single page app
because then you need to spin up an api
you need the
the server and an api when you use your
cypress tests or whatever
or a lot of people mock the api which
sometimes is fast
but can get out of sync in which case
you lose confidence in your tests
so having it in one spot is
i think really great and we do have the
capability to run
browser tests that's built into lucky
because i think it is still good to have
at least a couple smoke tests for your
critical paths
to test the happy path um but i mean
if you can write fewer of those that's
great
because they take forever to run for
sure yeah
in lucky there's a lot of features that
in other frameworks would be not usually
be included like for example there's
authentication you have this setup
check script to see if your app has all
of its dependencies
things like that i wonder if you could
sort of explain
sort of how you decided what sorts of
features should exist in the framework
versus being something that you leave to
the user to decide
i think things if there's no downside
for one thing if there's no downside
only upside
and almost everyone would benefit from
it i want to include it
so that's for example the system check
script
we also have a setup script and that's
what we tell people to use
instead of saying like first installed
yarn and
then run your migrations and blah blah
now our documentations don't even
mention that it's like
run script setup and the idea there
is it serves as kind of a best practice
it kind of pushes you into things to say
like hey
put stuff that you need in here then we
layered on the system check which also
runs before
setup and also every time you boot
the development environment where it'll
check
hey do you have a process manager which
you need it'll check
whether postgres is installed and
running because that's required
so if you go back to kind of that
criteria it's useful to pretty much
everyone
meaning like if postgres isn't running
and the app's not going to work
everyone would need to know that and it
doesn't really have a downside
if you don't want it for whatever reason
you just delete it or stop running it
that's not a huge downside that's like
you know one click
so that's part of why that's included i
don't like spending time on things that
aren't delivering actual real value
so i don't like spending time figuring
out why my
local environment is not working or
why it was working and now it suddenly
isn't
and with something like a system check
that makes teams happier in the sense
that let's say all of a sudden adds
somebody adds a new search capability
and it requires elastic search
and i do get pull from master do my
feature as soon as i boot the app
if they've added something to system
check that says hey you need elastic
it's going to tell me it's not going to
just blow up
it's going to be like hey you need
elasticsearch now install that and run
it
these are the types of things that i
really think are gonna
save a lot of time in terms of off
that's another one of those where it's
like so many people want it
and it should be easy and simple and not
like five different ways to do it
but not everyone wants it which is why
we made it optional
you choose in the wizard like if you
don't want off fine
i'd guess that most people generate it
with off i know i do
because i need it and the thing is we
also
changed how auth works in the sense that
it's mostly generated code
it's not just a bunch of calls to some
third-party library
so what that means is it is easy to
modify so if you want to
add email confirmations or invitations
or anything else like that
you're not mucking around in some
third-party library
it's code generated in your app that you
can see
and modify so it doesn't lock you into
anything it's very flexible and it helps
you get off the ground
running and that's why that was included
and i'm sure we're going to have other
stuff that may be included or
at least an option of being included in
the future
yeah i think one of the conversations
that people are having
now is particularly in the javascript
ecosystem
you end up pulling in a lot of different
dependencies you end up having to make a
lot of different decisions
and so it's interesting to sort of see
lucky kind of move back and
in the direction of say a rails of
trying to
kind of include the things that you
think probably
most people building an app are gonna
need yeah it's
a little more in that direction i think
on the flip side rails is starting to
include
so much that people are starting to get
mad almost
and it's like so much that you're like
what is this what is happening so we
want to strike a balance there and
so part of that is being very careful
about
what is included i think some of the
things that are included in rails could
just as easily be
added after the fact meaning 20 minutes
of work and you can add it
those are the types of things i probably
would not include
in lucky if it's 10 20 30 minutes to
you know add it and modify your app and
only
50 of people even want it we're probably
gonna just say
here's a guide on how to do it and make
it easy
but not do that as a generator if that
makes sense
what's an example of something like that
that would be pretty easy to add in
after the fact and
doesn't necessarily need to be included
well in rails 6 it's coming up they have
this action mailbox thing that handles
inbound emails
i'm pretty sure by default that is
included i could be wrong so don't quote
me on that but i've been seeing a lot of
twitter stuff lately of people being
super pissed about it so i think it's
there
that's something i definitely wouldn't
include because i think i've
written one app ever that uses inbound
emails
i mean github does too but i have not
written that
and a lot just don't have that so it's
odd to include it especially given the
fact that
it's not particularly hard to set up
yourself
i think based on on what i've seen or
action text is another one where
it has ways of making rich text editing
easier
that might be something too where it
could be added on later that
i think at least has a little bit more
merit because i think it's fairly
common first at some point to be like we
need a rich text editor
um but those are the kinds of things
that i would probably push
off and it's not a best practice either
meaning i think it's smart that it has
active record by default
and chooses a database for you because
it's best practice to just use active
record
right and you're going to have the best
time
using active record because that's what
everyone uses so including that
makes sense but but yeah something like
action mailbox is like
what's the benefit in including it yeah
just because the
majority of people who are writing
applications they'll never need that
inbound email feature as opposed to
your example of authentication like
probably the majority of applications
people are building will have
authentication in them exactly yeah
and it's something that's hard to add
meaning
um it touches so many parts of your
application
and because we are generating stuff it's
not easy to add after the fact
but stuff that is easy to add and easy
to remove
that another criteria is how easy is it
to remove it
so we include a few default css
styles but super easy to remove
it's basically like you go to your
it's like delete everything below this
line you delete it and it's like you're
done
but it's nice because it makes it look
decent and not like a horrific ugly
thing when you start your app right but
it's easy to remove and so that's
something for example that we also
include by default
that's also i think the distinction
between something that's
generated code and or configuration that
the
user can see i mean i think your setup
scripts
and your system check scripts one of the
things that makes those
kind of more straightforward is the fact
that they are in your code base
and they're they're bash scripts right
so yeah if you
want to modify it or you want to remove
it they're kind of right there
whereas something like a action text or
action mailbox
is probably in like the rails
gem right it's in the library so you
don't even see it in your code base
i guess that would be the distinction
there maybe yeah or you might but
you don't know why it's there or what it
does or
another concern is how many things does
it hook into so for example one of the
big things is
like i said default styles how many
places does that
hook into things just one you go to your
your main css file delete it but there's
a way to do that that i don't
particularly like i've seen some people
for example
use bootstrap or any framework it
doesn't matter what it is
the problem with those is it also
modifies the generated html
and the scaffold because by default it's
adding classes like column three
medium button blah blah blah blah if you
don't want to use bootstrap you have to
remove bootstrap and manually go through
all of the generated html files to
remove the bootstrap classes
and so that's like a key difference too
is how easy is it to remove
and we really want to only add things
that are easy to remove or really hard
to add
what what is the adoption of lucky look
like
do you know people using it in
production currently
yeah i don't have exact numbers which i
think is good because it
reduces anxiety a lot not knowing
i was like is it going up is it going
down but people are using it in
production
a lot from the very early days of
crystal one of our core
team members um jeremy he's been using
it at work
for two and a half three years
and they've had great success with it
they replaced some of their rails micro
services
with lucky originally for
the performance boost and i think this
is
common they stay for all the nice type
safety and the reliability they get
it's hard to explain with just words but
then you use it
and you see an error and we try and make
them nice not all of them are
but we try and make it nice people go oh
this is nice or people
are annoyed that they see this compiler
error
and then realize oh wait actually did
catch a bug
so but they're having great success um
big performance boost like something
like
they reduced their number of servers by
like 70
and their response times got cut down 60
or 70 percent
so yeah they're having great success and
then a few other people are building
client projects using lucky
i don't know what they are some people
there's just not
they can't say to the public
unfortunately but yeah people are using
in production which is really exciting
looking at the crystal community what
does that
look like you know is it pretty active
what are your thoughts on
the community yeah it's quite active
they've got sponsors quite quite a few
corporate sponsors so they're
making decent money to help fund
development
they're aiming for 1-0 i don't know
exactly when but they did a blog post
i'm saying it's going to be soon and
i've talked to them in person about it
but i don't know how much
you know i'm supposed to say but soon
which is fantastic because then you're
not going to have to deal with the
breaking changes
which have definitely been happening the
last two years and i think it's good
because the
language is improving and changing
things but once 100 hits people are
going to be able to jump in
and they're not going to have to update
their apps
every three months or whatever but yeah
a lot of participation
and the sponsorship money goes a long
way a lot of the development is based
in argentina and the dollar is super
strong over there
so meaning if you've got corporate
sponsorship in dollars
over here that goes a really long way
towards development
and they're all super nice i've talked
to a lot of them in person
super nice super smart guys the
community itself in terms of forums and
chats
that's where i'm a little hesitant it's
it's active
but i think not particularly welcoming
for newcomers
just really strong personalities very
smart but very strong personalities
and i would say it may be better to come
to the lucky chat rooms
we're very strict about our code of
conduct and not about nitpicky things
but just in general that
you know you talk to people with respect
and empathize and
we're not the type of people where you
come with a question we're like well did
you google it
we're gonna try and help you and so i
think it's a very welcoming community
and
even if you're not using lucky feel free
to hop
on our chat room if you go to the lucky
website there's a link
and uh yeah we're pretty nice over there
so things are moving forward
we're trying to to get to 1-0 around the
same time as crystal
uh maybe a little after but i think
that'll be a big milestone
it's it's interesting talking about the
community because i think
when you think about ruby one of the big
parts that attracts people is not
just the language or the framework but
it's you know
having an inclusive community having
people that are really
friendly so it's good to hear that lucky
you're striving to do that like why is
there that divide
ah i'm not entirely sure i mean part of
it is
i am a sensitive person and so i
am kind of trying to create the
community that i want which may be
actually way more
upbeat and positive just because i want
new people to feel comfortable
and i think maybe part of it is
with crystal they don't have that much
time i think as part of it and so it's
easier to brush stuff off
some of it could be just that they don't
care about the same things that i
personally do there's nothing actively
bad going on
it's just i prefer things rather than to
just be okay
average i want it to be exceptional
right
and a place where it's just like don't
worry you can say something
if it's you feel it's dumb we're not
gonna be like pile on we're gonna be
like hey it's fine and here's maybe an
alternative
so yeah i mean go to the crystal rooms i
still do i still get help
there's a lot of really smart people um
you just got to put on like a little
thicker skin and be prepared for
like why do you want to do this have you
tried this other thing have you done
this other thing
in a way it's a good thing because
they're making sure
that like you've tried your different
options and you're not just asking to do
something that's a horrible idea
but it can make people i think feel like
their idea is getting attacked
or whatever so that's what i mean by
part of it is just like if you're
sensitive
that's gonna come off as probably
harsher than it
was intended um but you can still get a
lot of help
yeah i guess it's just trying to find
the right level of
yeah i don't know what the word would be
but yeah making people feel
comfortable yeah i do have a really high
bar for that because like
i am sensitive and i grew when
i learned a program all online with
books with forums
and i remember how hard it was as a new
developer that didn't know best
practices and people would be like why
are you even trying to do that
it's so stupid and it's like dude i've
been programming for like six months
calm down
yeah and i think it's common i think i
mean that happened in the ruby forums
it happened in the rails forums it's a
common thing
i think across the internet and various
communities
so it may not even be that crystal's
particularly bad
it's probably a lot like most
communities but we just want ours to be
exceptional in terms of making people
feel welcome and
you know if someone has a bad idea and
an air quote's bad because
maybe it's a great idea we just don't
have the context but if it is a bad idea
we're not to say why are you doing that
blah blah first let's help you solve
your problem
and then talk about how might this be
better
maybe there's a better way to do it and
it just feels a lot better people are
more accepting
too of your feedback when you're not
just immediately jumping on them
and say why are you even trying to do
that and so i think that's important
yeah i mean i think that probably
applies to really all projects right
like they could all kind of stand to
learn
from some of that and kind of see it
from the other person's perspective
who doesn't have sort of all the
the same knowledge that you know you've
been building up and
maybe they can bring you a new
perspective as well that you didn't you
didn't even think about yeah
yeah total i mean we've changed stuff
and lucky
a lot of stuff that i was pretty sure
about and
they asked if it could be done
differently
shared their use case and it's like oh
yeah i made a mistake
and so it's good for everyone like if
you
show a little bit of vulnerability and
openness
you're much more likely to learn and
you're much more likely to learn
new and novel things because the people
with the strongest opinions
are often the ones that have that
opinion based on
some principle they read about or a talk
or
something else it's the quiet people
that are like hey
can we try doing this like a little
differently and you're like
whoa i've never thought of this because
no one else has
but you're new you came up with this
great new innovative idea
and you felt comfortable sharing because
we're not just shooting people down
constantly
and so yeah i wish more communities did
that in general
because it's mutually beneficial that's
kind of a good place to start
wrapping up but where should people go
if they want to
learn more about lucky first place
luckyframework.org
that's the main website it has guides it
has blog posts that you can
follow or subscribe to with new
announcements
and it has a link to our chat room as
well as the github
so that's where i'd go feel free to hop
on the chat room
anytime we're all really helpful
and try and be nice and so like people
shouldn't
hesitate to run in there if they have
problems um
if there's stuff that's confusing feel
free to open an issue
unlucky we have a tag that's like
improve
error experience so we have dedicated
stuff
just to do that yeah in fact if you
start a lucky project and you get a
compile time error when you first start
or are fresh on a project it says hey if
you're still stuck
go to our chat room and ask for help
everyone should feel free to do that
very cool and how can people follow you
and see what you're up to
paul c smith on twitter probably the
best way to do it right now
maybe one day i'll have a blog or
something but right now it's twitter
cool well uh paul thank you so much for
coming on the show
yeah thanks for having me i really
enjoyed it this has been jeremy jung for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening
developers take your marks it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris
it's time to deliver complex mission
critical applications in the fastest
route possible
it's time to use any data from any
source it's time to embed analytics and
create
interactive user interfaces so what are
you waiting for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
intersystems iris data platform the
fastest way to build applications
ready set code
start coding for free visit
intersystems.com
try to try iris
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening